No.
OK.
So.
Oops, I have to share the screen.
Screen sharing.
So um.
Uh.
Sorry for the little delay,
but it was raining.
So did you have some spend some time in
trying to figure out what I told you
during the last class?
I mean that.
Comments or questions or doubts?
So your colleague says to me promises
from JavaScript were a good way to sort
of figure out is the opposite.
I mean promises are a particular kind of
monad like the async.
In a sharp, so historically the.
Monads started mostly to preserve pure
functional PROGRAMMING in a work with
state,
because basically the monad allows you to
hide the state inside the monad and then
have a a pure functional approach.
That is simply a sequence of function
application of the bind to transform an
hidden state.
And in this way basically you hide under
the carpet the state and this applies to
a lot of things including concurrency.
So yes,
you're right in the sense that
asynchronous programming.
So if you're familiar with promises,
it's OK,
but it's important that you understand
that it's an instance of a more general
pattern.
Because if you recognize this,
then suddenly the probability
distributions,
the synchronous programming,
the sequences,
and many others are simply instances of
the same pattern.
And the pattern is I have a value I build
around a container for this value.
I define basically an algebra between the
containers and at each step I obtain I
get a new container.
With the same type of content,
with a different type of content,
and in promises,
what you learned is the so-called
continuation passing style.
At some point we will dedicate a class to
asynchronous PROGRAMMING from a language,
not from concurrency.
From concurrency there are other courses.
But what does it mean to have
asynchronous PROGRAMMING inside a
PROGRAMMING language? Because basically.
Almost all the modern asynchronous
constructs that we have in PROGRAMMING
languages promises is 1, async in C#,
async in F# and many others basically
introduce a continuation passive style.
So basically you have the perception
there is a lot of the sugaring and as you
can see the sugaring is keeping popping
up in our conversations.
Basically you have the impression to
define.
Atomic computation and like a very
traditional function,
but in fact this will be compiled as a
sequence of computation with a state that
is hiddenly passed.
So that the formal semantics hopefully
will remain true,
but at the same time you are generating
under hood the number of functions that
will be called at the end of the previous
invocation.
And that that is a style of PROGRAMMING
that is traditionally known as
continuation passing style.
In in the past, especially in JavaScript,
the use was to be explicit.
So basically you start defining.
It was typically in Ajax programming.
You you define your code,
then you you make the Ajax call and you
set.
The function to be invoked upon
completion,
and that is basically the same thing.
So the promise gives you just a more
cleaner way to do exactly the same thing.
Right. And by the way,
continuation passing style is a form of
functional PROGRAMMING and now has become
popular because most of the PROGRAMMING
languages we use today are.
Object oriented, imperative, functional.
All together.
OK,
so today and tomorrow we will introduce
something that.
Is at the same time a new chapter,
but also it will also be a sort of
exercise on functional PROGRAMMING
because F sharp.
As uh some uh feature that uh is called
quotations.
Which is a feature of F sharp,
and so in this respect is a very specific
feature,
but basically allows me to introduce a
much more general notion.
Which is the the meta programming, OK.
Um.
What it is meta programming?
Meta PROGRAMMING is uh um.
A very simple idea,
a program which generates or and or
manipulates a program.
OK. Or and or reason about the program.
OK,
so it's meta because basically the
program reason typically.
About itself.
So a compiler is technically not a full
meta program because it's a program that
generates another program given a source
coding input.
So it's true that it manipulates.
The program.
It's true that there's a lot of similar
things and the tools are the same,
but strictly speaking,
meta PROGRAMMING is mostly intended
programs that reason about themselves.
Or modify their own behaviour at runtime.
OK,
so there are several ways of performing
metaprogramming. It's.
It's counterintuitive, but it requires.
So in many ways metaprogramming is one of
the most important tools for - ADVANCED
programming, I would say,
because both for.
An - ADVANCED programmer that write the
code and also an - ADVANCED programmer
which read the code.
Give you an example before digging into
more code if you go.
In the.
A leisure record base.
Has been developed using.
A standard frameworkasp.
net so it's like Java or whatever.
And it's interesting to look at the
startup code.
Which requires some zoom.
Um.
Which is interesting because.
Uh,
you basically the the there is no main
program.
Which is not entirely correct if I
remember well.
So there is a program.
There there is a program.
The program has uh.
Um, a main method then?
The main method.
Uh.
The main method that simply says.
Create create a house builder.
Given the arguments, build and run.
That's it. OK, so.
You say OK,
where is this create host builder?
There we are.
So the create host builder is a.
It's scaffolded,
which means that basically there is a
code generator that generates the
template that typically everybody use and
many of the asp.net developers never.
Look into that code, nevertheless.
You have a.
Static class host.
So you create the default builder,
you configure the logging,
you configure web host defaults.
And web user user setup setup.
Now even and here we're not even touching
the meta programming part.
I mean we here there are a lot of things
happening. I mean,
so this is a static method.
There are a number of static classes with
methods that are.
Invoked and then there is a.
Uh.
Function that is passed in the to the
configure web host defaults.
So a little bit of functional programming
and the function expected by this method
requires a function that given an object
of type web builder.
You do something with that web builder.
You don't know when this function will be
invoked.
You have no idea on how the framework
will invoke this function,
but you know that at some point
eventually you will be invoked and when
you will be invoked and you have a web
builder object that has been prepared.
For you.
You invoke the you start top and you pass
a type and technically that is a generic
method.
Andrea next week we'll talk about
parametric poly several type of
polymorphy.
So you will learn a little bit bit more
about that, but basically is.
Is a function with a type parameter like
TK that we we introduce it with F sharp
or ML or Askell etcetera and and and
start up is a class of mine.
OK, so uh, in fact that when uh,
I will be invoked eventually.
The startup class will be used
instantiated and used by that piece of
code.
And this is a a class of mine.
I will receive a configuration interface
object,
an environment with the web web host that
I can do something and and then
eventually someone because the startup
class.
Uh uh.
Osess a number of methods.
Interesting.
Start up is a class.
Do you think that this class inherits
from?
Object with C#.
C# is very similar to in many ways to
Java, so setup is up.
Do you see any interface implementation?
No.
So why someone tell me this method gets
called by the runtime?
Use this method to add services to the
container.
Not possible.
Not through the interface pattern that
you're familiar with.
It is possible because of a function that
has become.
Really, really important.
That is called reflection. OK, so.
The reflection is the ability of the
program.
Of reasoning about itself.
So reflection typically allows you to,
I don't know,
given an object to get a class which
represent the class of that object.
To that class you can ask a class.
Do you? What are your methods?
What are the decorations of your methods?
What is the body ideally of of your
method? OK, what are the fields?
And that is the reflection part.
Of the of a META program,
inspecting the state of the program
itself, not just the values, OK.
And then there is also the intersection
part which is set invoke. OK,
so you can dynamically invoke methods.
By asking support of the runtime.
So of course reflection and intersection
requires some runtime support to be
supported by the language.
So C++ has no reflection.
At runtime,
if you have a appointed to an object,
there's no way to get the class of that
object and understand how that particular
class is possible. Java was the first one.
Oh, sorry.
It's it's not it's been the the the
system that made popular reflection OK.
Reflection is available,
I mean is available in many forms since
Lisp, since the 60s and the 70s,
so it's not so so new.
The reflection that we are used to has
been defined mostly by Java.
And um.
So this method gets called because
through reflection the system looks for
the methods in the startup class and say
OK,
there is the configuration service
configure service with this signature.
Yes, invoke it.
OK,
of course you're paying runtime type
costs.
But this is only once you can afford it.
It's not that expensive. OK,
it's the cost that an interpreter will
sustain when you call a function inside
an interpreter.
Because an interpreter we discussed about
interpret,
but it's fairly obvious that when the
interpreter reads.
The function definition.
It has an internal table with all the
functions,
and when you see the function code,
you go and look up in that in that table
and invoke the the the an interp.
You start the interpretation of that
function. OK, so basically.
This means that at runtime you will need
some information in order to be able to
execute this code,
but it is expensive if it's if you invoke
this function multiple time in a loop.
But once in the execution of a program is
basically neglecting all the cost of
browsing and invoking. OK,
because then of course the runtime
optimize the the thing, so it assemble.
The activation record that we will
explore later in the course and activate
the function.
So the execution function is like it's
compiled.
So it's just the cost of finding and
invoking the function that you pay at
runtime. OK during the 90s.
Everybody was scared about this because
the PCs were not that efficient. Nowadays,
honestly,
even a Raspberry Pi is efficient enough
to do this thing without basically not
noticing the difference with other
different approaches.
And and so as I hope you see.
In in in this,
this is the modern way of programming.
Someone will call you at some point you.
There's no way to go and look.
For a main and then you start follows the
program definition from the main method
of function because eventually you will
invoke some library.
This library will say OK,
I take care of you.
So be prepared that some eventually I
will call you back to to do something. OK.
This has become very popular in the 90s
thanks to UI graphical programming. OK.
Event driven programming was the origin
of all this because basically the
windowing system has the events,
tracks the interrupts of the mouse and
the keyboard.
It has the motion of the current window
that has the.
The focus we are used to and so if I type
a keyboard, a keyboard,
it's not the program that reads the
keyboard,
but the windowing system detects the
keyboard,
looks to the current windows from the
windows, look to the thread.
And the process and insert a message in a
standard queue,
which is the event queue that belongs to
that process.
The process does a very simple loop,
next event, process the event, next event.
So it basically.
Reads the events from the queue and
process the event is basically a big
switch that invokes your.
Depressed method. OK,
so that is basically the origin of all
this event driven programming.
Event driven programming basically is a
reactive form of programming.
So you react basically to external events
in graph.
Programming typically are bound to time
and devices,
and then once you get the control,
you perform actions.
Typically you change the state of your
interface or you render the current frame
of.
Component that is in a very few words,
the graphical programming.
At some point we found out that that is
not that bad.
It applies to a lot of other environments,
not just the graphics,
for instance to to asynchronous
programming,
because when you start an asynchronous
activity,
eventually you want to receive the.
Event activity completed.
So we started using the callback.
Callback is the standard name for the
function that will be invoked at the end
of some process.
You will be called back and you will
receive some data that describes the
partic in graphics is the data which
represents the event,
so the key press the the position of the
mouse or something.
In in in asynchronous programming,
it will contain an object that you will
get an object with the result of a
computation and eventual value produced
by the computation. OK, same idea.
And and once this idea started becoming
popular in the during the 90s,
it started permeating all the programming
in all the frameworks.
So most of the programming frameworks we
use today.
Are reactive frameworks in which you
through thanks to the functional
programming part that has been
implemented by all the programming
language by now or most of them.
Basically you register your own function
as a callback some.
More and more bigger runtime do a lot of
work for you. In case of graphics,
it was to manage the frame buffer,
to manage the interrupts,
etcetera in a web application,
the connections, etcetera,
and you will be invoked only.
When your intervention is needed.
So it's a super nice pattern to reuse
large code bases to the point in which it
becomes difficult to understand the
execution of your program because you
have no clue.
Of what happens before the invocation and
after the invocation,
not only in graphics and in many other
and in web you you're not all you give up.
To the sequence.
In imperative programming,
first there is a statement,
then there is another statement,
then another one, then another one. OK,
you have control of what come first and
what comes second. You can.
Prove that your variable will contain a
given value because of that.
Weak graphical programming and.
Evan driven programming,
and so basically any form of programming
nowadays,
you lose control about the sequence in
which the runtime will invoke your
methods or your functions.
So you know that the bottom will be
pressed. You have no clue.
Of uh.
What happened before the press of the
button?
So you will start digging inside your
state because every component,
every reaction will basically write some
variable, say.
This has happened and so when you will be
invoked, you look at what, what,
what is the current state of the world
and you will react to that. OK,
so this is a general pattern that has
become so pervasive that any framework
available today.
Is.
By framework I mean not the programming
language,
but a set of libraries written developing
in some programming language has become
supervasive that I I can't imagine
programming without understanding this.
Apart from very few programmers that
write a good old application,
there are sections in which good old
programming with the main and everything
and everything is under your control
still happens.
Internet of Things.
So if I if I program a remote control
system,
there you will find a more traditional
way of programming. But apart from that,
everything else is basically a runtime
that someone picked up.
You record your call callbacks.
You react to those callbacks.
And and so the callback notion is very
important is what a function that will be
invoked with some arguments upon some
external event.
So it was important to be able to.
It was very important to be able to um.
I was checking the time.
It was very important to to be able to
pass a a function as a reaction of some
external event. OK,
first attempt object oriented programming.
Oh, nice.
The the the class has its own internal
state. Oh yeah, so I can record.
I can use that internal state of the of
the of the class as the blackboard where
I keep track of the state.
As long as my methods are invoked. OK,
so method is invoked event fields shared
state.
I check the shared state and I implement
the behavior I need.
Nice.
And how can I be?
Can I be sure that there is the mouse
button down method in my class?
I got an idea interface.
I start as a framework where there is the
the class that inherits from some
abstract class that I call component and
through inheritance I impose a number of
methods that.
Then I know they are there.
And that's good.
We we made this work working for at least
two decades using interfaces and classes
that you know by heart,
mostly because they're super useful in
the modern programming.
You know what?
And if I take two frameworks that
performs basically the same work and I
would wanted to make them interact,
then I have a problem because one
framework has the class component and the
other framework has the class control.
They do the same thing,
but they are different types.
They both have left button mouse clicked
method,
but nevertheless because they use
different interface,
they are incompatible.
So as programmers we we want always more
and say can we address this problem?
Because this object orientation is very
nice, but it's not perfect.
Can we do something better?
And someone said.
You know what?
I just need the mouse button down
signature.
I don't care about having a class
interface.
As long as you give me the mouse left
button mouse method signature,
I will invoke that.
OK. And and in fact, uh, that was, uh,
I would say.
2008910 more or less.
The so-called duck typing became popular.
It is called duck typing because
basically it says if I have a a class
that packs and and walks.
Like a duck, then he's a duck.
And there was and that philosophically it
was very important because that was the
start of Python JavaScript as a
mainstream programming languages because
they were able to define a sort of weaker
typing because we.
I said that in JavaScript,
everything is a dictionary,
so you don't really care about the class.
The class is not so strict as it is in
Java, C++, and.net, etcetera,
but I still retain this ability of invoke.
The the method that I presume, uh,
will do something just by the name.
Nice.
Then when you start scaling up a system
without typing, we human,
we like to think that we are perfect,
that we are consistent, but we're not.
You start writing a program in a style by
the end of the.
Development,
you change it completely style.
So it's very,
very difficult to be consistent with
ourselves.
We discussed this when we were talking
about the memory and it is true also for
the rest of the programming.
I mean we fail to agree upon ourselves
about the convention about.
Allocating and allocating heap memory,
figure out everything else and we said
Rust is wonderful because it introduced
basically convention by definition in the
language so that everybody has to buy to
that and not.
Something else.
So going back to my original point,
thanks to the reflection and the ability
to invoke at runtime dynamically.
Part of your program,
you can go beyond classes and interfaces
and invoke a method just because it has a
particular signature.
So this is similar to what you can do in
Python and in JavaScript and in less
strictly. I mean they are strictly type.
Technically they don't have type
constructor in.
This is the counterpart in a world where
you can define your own types.
And this is possible just because of meta
programming.
So to really understand a modern code,
you need to understand meta programming
because the most of the programs nowadays
tend to reason about themselves to
provide useful features.
You want to see an example I.
Show you so.
Let me go in the controller.
And let's take the a leader API.
Anna.
You know what?
Let's take this code.
This code is sort of sum up of most of
the things that I told you until today.
So it's a synchronous. OK,
we already discussed that.
We will discuss again.
OK,
it's an asynchronous method and and so we
know that it's not a real function.
It will become some more complicated.
It is called listed.
Sorry listed elections.
And this is annotated.
This is annotated,
so this list elections is mapped onto an
HTTP GET called election.
So basically,
thanks to the ability of reading the
definition of the program itself,
I can write a program that transform.
A method of a class into an HTTP request.
So if in the system you call the a region
API slash API slash version 1.
0 slash election.
And.
An optional argument that you can pass,
then you will get this method executed.
So you you issue an HTTP request,
you get a method executed.
Lots of work behind.
You have to implement a web server,
you have to implement all the HTTP
protocol,
you have to implement the security.
The identity and many other things,
and eventually you can get this
invocation method performed on your
behalf. Thanks to reflection,
I can write a program because it's always
the same work that does all this work for
me.
And so I can simply say OK,
this method is on STP is called election
and whenever you see the get verb on that
particular URL you have to invoke this.
And you know what I also get type
checking because if you try to pass.
Something other than a Boolean value,
I would get an error because an error
because a Boolean value is expected. OK,
so.
All these to try to make you see the
importance of metaprogramming.
It's not some geeky thing of people that
likes to write compilers is the core of.
Any framework we use today, Python,
there is a,
there is a different way of doing,
but there are lots of Python frameworks
that allows you to annotate methods.
That will be exposed in as HTTP GET
invocation exactly with the same approach.
OK, so you can change the language,
but basically the idea is the same.
At some point we felt the need for our
program.
To be able to inspect themselves,
not because they like they are.
They like the the mirror to see them on
in the mirror,
but because we can develop libraries that
implement sophisticated behaviours and
can.
Look at the because the program is made
of two things.
You're part of a program or three things.
You're part of a program,
the libraries you are using in your
program and the runtime of your program.
OK,
so the point is that the libraries to to
be more and more useful.
Need to know about the part you wrote of
the program and metaprogramming is the
answer to that.
So metaprogramming started in the origin
as a way to change the semantic of the
programming language,
as we will shortly see. But honestly,
that was just the beginning. Today,
program metaprogramming is basically the
core of.
Most of the most used programming
framework today in libraries you use
React on JavaScript in React JS for your
web pages. That is the meta program.
You prefer AngularJS? Same story.
And in that case,
the library parses the Dom and the Dom
gets interpreted and the semantics of the
Dom gets changed by the library itself,
and you get a lot of nice services
because of that.
OK,
so basically meta programming has become
the dominant way of writing complex
programs,
which means that you must become familiar
with this because otherwise you will fail
to understand the behaviour of a program.
Because you can understand what this
particular method does,
but you will fail to understand why and
when it will be invoked.
OK,
so that's the reason because meta
programming is crucial for you to
understand.
And Java, the story is nice.
Java introduced the the notion, so.
Let me for a second,
let me start a terminal.
We the um.
With the.net FSI with F#. I mean,
I'm using F# not because of F# here.
I mean it's just a way to show you a live
example of reflection. OK, so.
If I.
I have a string I can say dot get type.
And I have and and I receive an object
which describes with a lot of fields and
methods which describes the string class.
And so I can then say get methods.
I hope that is the name and this is the
list of the methods of.
Of the of the the string. So for instance,
let's take the list one.
You see how many data is there.
So this is the join.
It is contained in the module which is
called like this.
It is implemented in intermediate
language. These are flags.
There are tokens that have some purpose,
of course,
but this is not the moment to stress this.
It is a static method.
It's static through. It's not virtual.
It's not a virtual method.
So any decoration in your types when you
perform.
All that effort to describe your your
type is basically documented in a
database that is generated by the
compiler and is part of the binary system.
Hmm. So that at runtime,
the runtime gives you the ability to read
that information.
And thanks to that you can reason about O
at at some point someone said.
So we got this database,
that database which is a tree that
represents all the definition of my
program because of course you also have
the the bytecode if you want,
but the bytecode is not in the source
language. So first important observation.
Reflection has become useful because the
typing has been brought to runtime,
so the string class string class.
That you type in in your program is the
same string class that the runtime is
using to execute.
The more the compiler generate types on
your behalf.
You remember when we look at into the the
sugaring of the state machine of the C#
compiler.
Then you have a class that has generated
name that you didn't write for
implementing the comprehension.
That class is available through
reflection,
but for you it's less useful because it's
not your class.
It's some generated thing by the compiler
you're not even aware about. OK, so.
It's interesting to be able to reflect
the state of your program at runtime as
long as the objects that you reason about
are present both in the source language
and in the target language.
Otherwise it's useless. So after Java,
this means types,
because most of the types are still
written by programmers, OK,
and that makes them useful.
But it's important that you imagine that
I have my source program.
I don't have the source program at
runtime,
I have the compiled program apart from
JavaScript, which of course.
You have the Swiss program too at runtime,
but for most of the programs out there,
you don't have the source code,
you have the compiled version,
so you retain enough information in the
binary to do useful things.
OK,
and you have the sensation that you're
browsing the source code, but you're not.
You're reading the methods because the
runtime has the very same notion at
compile time and in the language of types
and methods.
And because that objects are shared
between the source language and the
target language,
you have the impression that it's the
same thing.
OK,
so that's the reason why it is popular to
browse at runtime through reflection
types, not code,
because the code is typically deleted
during the computation process and it
will be impractical to have.
The code there, right?
OK.
So now someone say you know we already
generated the list election method with a
return type, public or not, virtual not,
static or not, etcetera, etcetera.
All the qualification of the details the
compiler is already emitting or.
These things, you know, I got an idea.
Let's have.
Uh,
an extra annotation mechanism so that I
can put custom annotation to my method.
And notice that was invented by Java,
but the problem is that that annotation
bits were made available in the binary,
but there was no way to define them in
the language.
So Java Runtime implemented custom
attributes since the very beginning,
but Java language had no way to include
this information in your binary.
It was a compiler thing, OK.
dot net few years later said come on,
are you serious?
Let let's expose this into the language
so that programmers can put their own
annotation onto types.
That is interesting.
And because of that,
basically you have the ability to
annotate in a formal way.
So it is more than a comment because it
has a semantics.
Technically this is a class that must
inherit from the attribute class.
So there are some constraints it may have.
Values,
but those values should be computed at
compile time.
So clearly they should go into the
metadata so it can be generated runtime,
but nonetheless I can and it's an array.
So every class, method,
field and every object has a custom
attribute array of things,
so the join method.
As no custom attribute of the class
string. OK,
now if I'm able to label with the
information part of my program that this
annotation have no semantics in C#.
Those are like comments,
but those are available through the
reflection API and so if you are using
reflection,
you can alter the behaviour of the
program according to these custom
annotations.
So from the programming language
standpoint,
that is just a bunch of data that is
included in the metadata of your
programming inside the binary,
and that's it. It has no semantics.
But when you use the reflection API,
suddenly you can give semantics and it's
not fixed by the language.
You can decide your own semantics in your
program.
OK,
and if I'm implementing a web framework,
I can say OK if I have a class which
inherits from controller and all the
methods are target like HTTP get,
this means that.
This function should be invoked only
through the GET verb,
not through the post verb of HTTP.
And this annotation means nothing to the
C compiler.
It's the runtime that by browsing the
reflection information.
Accesses and changes the behavior of this
thing OK.
And so, as you can see,
the full system has a lot of inherited
services because of this reflection
authorized roles.
I can have declarative programming.
I declare how what I need.
I don't say how I need.
I will get it.
OK here I say OK this election ID blah
blah is available on throughput and only
if the user has this role election
officer. Otherwise this shouldn't be.
Uh, accessible.
This is super cool.
Because I don't have to go in my
programming.
If current user is in this role,
do this and do that is a property that I
can even safely type check.
I can prove that this thing is accessible
because if you do if in your program,
if you forget or if you're wrong,
write the wrong condition in your if
statement,
you may lead access to a code to a user
that shouldn't have access to that code.
In this way I declared that and then if I
prove that the runtime ensure that only
authorized role can go through that piece
of code,
then these apply to all the programs and
so I can be sure that if you don't have
that role you can't access to this thing.
Unless of course bugs of implementation.
So it's very different because if I have
4 methods with the rice roles,
I'm sure that all of them will be applied
in the right way if I use either user is
enrolled and I type check the role.
Then if I forget or I write the wrong
condition,
then my my program will be broken in one
of the four methods and three will be OK.
OK,
so I hope that in this very long
introduction to meta programming to have
convinced you that you have to spend lots
of time not in, I mean studying.
Of course I like if you study.
Monads, languages, parses, etcetera.
You should. You have to pass an exams,
of course,
but please spend your time and become
better programmers.
Spend your time in trying to understand
every nuance, every symbol in.
Piece of code,
because even this very small casual code
I came up with, it's full of things,
full of it's dense of semantics.
There is this async which basically says
the compiler will desugar this in a.
So this is not a method,
it will be compiled in several methods.
You're curious, you ask the AI,
which is the fastest way how to browse
the intermediate language of net compiler
program.
Like this, look at the binary.
You will find that there are a lot.
There will be this method plus many other
methods to implement all the asynchronous
programming there is.
A little bit of type inference.
COM is of type Poly Station Commission
and the compiler, in a very stupid way,
is capable of inferring that COM is of
type that.
There are genetics, yes,
so parametric types.
Um.
There is something that we didn't explore
yet, but we will between today,
most likely tomorrow.
The C# compiler implements a subset of
syntax that is known as language
integrated query.
Which is Link and Link allows you to have
a sort of SQL like syntax from C in this
where condition to manipulate objects and
collections and not just the database.
And this will be the sugared in the
creation of a data structure that some
driver will compile into a query for a
specific database.
OK at runtime and so this particular
thing is.
Part of the the sugaring process and and
then there is a little bit of high order
programming. I'm passing a Lambda.
Uh,
function that that it will be invoked the.
To avoid the for each because here I.
Perform the query asynchronous.
So I start the query, I suspend myself.
When the query is ready,
I take back the control and then I have a
list and and and and I invoke convert all
which is basically the map.
Function.
So for every value of the source list,
I get new list with a function that is
applied to every to every element of the
source list,
and this distinction list is the
transformed list. OK, so as you can see.
In very few lines of code,
there are a lot of interaction between
the compiler, the way the compiler,
the sugar things, the semantics, types,
type checking, etcetera.
Genetics, et cetera.
The runtime and the libraries that come
with the language that provide part of
the semantics. So guess what?
Modern programming languages are
difficult to define without standard
libraries.
Because part of the behavior is defined
in outside libraries and so on. OK,
and most of this evolution in recent
years is due to meta program because.
The types were not enough to support the
our need of reuse our code,
so we look for other means of reusing our
codes by writing frameworks that
manipulate.
Smaller and smaller part of the program.
So if you look at how much code you are
writing and how much code you are using,
how much code your program is made with,
you are writing more and more a smaller
portion.
Of the of the program.
And the rest,
the rest is provided by the frameworks
that you have to understand and and for
this reason when I was I started writing
CGI application during the 90s,
I was master of myself.
Today you may be familiar with Angular JS
and no.
Nothing about React JS or vice versa.
So you are not anymore an expert of web,
you are an expert of Angular.
Which is a very small part of a larger
world. OK,
and of course a true web programmer knows
about the Dom,
knows out about the implementation of
Angular or Reactor and understands what
the framework does and appreciate that is
saving a lot of time because otherwise.
Would have been involved in doing a lot
of things,
but most of the programmers out there
have no clue about React. I mean,
it's like the Bible. React is like this.
Sorry, I have no idea of how it works.
Right. So let's go back to original.
So now that we did this very long but
important introduction, let's now focus.
We already explored a little bit of
reflection. I've shown you the F sharp,
which is a.
We went to C#, Java,
same get class instead of get type,
but basically same thing in Python and in
JavaScript. How does it work reflection?
In JavaScript there,
some of you were nodding about.
What is the fundamental construct of
reflection in JavaScript?
How you see the prototype?
There is a construct in the language
which is the reflection,
which is the four four.
N in O where N is the name of a property
O is an object.
So basically you can enumerate the names
of a dictionary that is the reflection in
JavaScript.
Through that you can start reading all
the properties and then you can use type
of which is the other part of reflection
in JavaScript and ask for the type of the
of the class and so on and so forth.
OK and you can then say if type of a
string then do this,
if it's number do that, etcetera.
Right. So as you can see,
you change the language,
you get different degree of support. Why?
Because for instance,
JavaScript is interpreted like Python.
Interpreted languages allows you to have
eval.
Because if you have the interpreter,
you have at runtime for sure the parser
and the and the interpreter. OK,
so in interpreter programming languages
often provide eval.
The eval function takes as input a string
which is assumed to be.
A string in the language and invokes the
interpreter on that string.
So meta programming in interpreted
language is much easier,
is also error prone.
Because I can be a bad programmer and I
can generate A syntax error in the string
and then I will get a syntax error. OK.
So someone start saying OK.
You show me an example of quasi quotation.
Of lisp.
So Lisp said this processing. Lisp said,
you know,
let's have a standard syntax where data
and program everything is the same and
then interpreter with.
Interpret the thing so in Lisp.
You can basically.
So at least everything is an S expression.
An S expression is open, open brace,
a sequence of symbol is a list basically.
No and and close, close brace. Um and so.
Letter.
Requires a list of assignments.
So this is let.
This is the argument of let and this is
the first and is X takes 10, Y takes 20.
And uh, Lisp introduced the.
The.
This back tick back quote notation for
the quasi quotation.
So what is the quotation?
Let's think a little bit about this
important notion in programming languages.
In your opinion.
Why we use quotes around strings?
What is the true message between the
quotes?
You're saying please ignore this is text
is not program.
Hmm.
OK.
There are situation in which you.
Both the code and not the same.
Do you have a an example of this?
Hmm, that's.
SQL is a different story.
PHP.
In PHP code is quoted. Why?
Because most of the text of a web page is
static, so it is much more.
It makes more sense to quote the code
rather than quoting the text.
OK,
so quote and un quote basically defines 2
languages, 2 languages.
One is the program, the other is the data.
Always. In some cases you call the code,
other cases you call the text.
But nevertheless you need a syntax to
discriminate between these two levels.
This should be preserved at runtime.
This should be executed.
Right now.
Lis says OK because in my language
everything is an expression.
I have an interpreter then I'd like to
generate.
Part of the program.
Which is basically generating a list and
I like it to not use the quote.
I I don't want to give you the text
because the text is error prone if in the
text.
If in the text I write.
Oh, yes, not the plus, plus, plus. OK, uh,
should be OK.
So.
Singing in the rain if I write.
1-2 let's say add the one.
This will be add 1-2. This is correct.
OK in Lisp Lisp as a syntax which we
calls Lambda calculus.
So function arguments.
By the way.
If you replace this with that,
you obtain another language that you may
have faced if you.
Are more mathematical.
That is Mathematica from Wolfram uses.
Square braces,
but basically it's like lis, OK.
This just to say, OK,
Lisp apart from E Max is still there
because all those that are using Wolfram
Mathematica are using dialect of Lisp.
OK, but I can write add one, add, add 2-3.
Or and this is,
I mean this is easy to spot,
but nevertheless is syntactically
syntactically not correct because I have
an extra.
Race.
So the risk of using streams to specify
code in our meta program,
because of course meta programming is
made. I read the state of the program.
Eventually I want to manipulate the
program fairly natural. OK.
If I am in a compiled language that is
more complicated in.
net when we explored the whitespace
compiler you if you remember I generated
the.
By code OK.
It would be nice to be able to manipulate
the source code and add the code
generated for me.
If you are very, very motivated,
I can send you my PhD thesis that was
about exactly this, this, this problem.
How can we get?
quotation in a compiled language like.net.
Um, OK.
So the quasi quotation is important.
You have to learn the quasi quotation
because it influences all the meta
programming choices after since then. OK,
so the quasi quotation is a notation is a
concept.
It's like the PHP code quotation.
I mean it's a concept that has been
declined several time along the history.
So the quasi quotation is introduced by
the backtick. OK,
so that the language knows that the S
expression that will follow.
Is quasi quoted. OK,
so the quasi quotation is like commas in
strings.
So this one should not be interpreted,
it should be taken as it is, right?
But that is not a string,
is an S expression.
So it's a fragment of a program that I
want. I don't want to interpret.
Now I want to defer the execution of this.
OK now.
But you know, if I let me take this.
Uh, so.
If I write this.
OK,
in in Lisp there is also the quotation.
The quotation is like commas,
like quotes for strings. OK,
so I'm returning this.
So if I return these X&
Y will be X&Y.
But I just said that X is 10 and Y is 20.
So I want the quotation,
but I'd like to see 10 and 20 here
substituted.
That is what I want.
So I don't want a full quotation.
I don't want to have the a monolithic
block of code.
I want to say I want to build a piece of
code that in part is quoted and in part I
want the actual value now.
So.
The quasi quotation syntax is basically
this.
It allows you to quote a piece of code.
And say where,
which basically means I want to defer the
execution of this code and then I have an
un quote operation that say yes,
but please X should be.
The actual value of X,
not the symbol X that should be returned.
OK, so.
The quasi quasi quotation mechanism
always has two levels.
You are be able to quote to say OK this
piece of code is the output I want and un
quote but here evaluate because I need
the value not the symbol.
Right. You see the point.
If you think of PHP,
now you understand PHP much better than
before,
because basically it's exactly this. OK,
when you say you evaluate an expression,
that is OK.
It's it's this part.
It's not exactly the same thing because
you're not manipulating the the code,
you're manipulating HTML.
So it's slightly different,
but basically similar in here. OK,
you're manipulating when you mix Python,
sorry PHP.
And and JavaScript that is similar.
It's not exactly the same,
but it's similar.
OK.
Now that we introduce the quasi quotation
syntax, we can go back to F#.
And there are the nested quasi quotation.
By the way,
I stressed the AI at the beginning.
I'm not keep stressing the AI because
this is not a course about the AI,
it's about advanced programming.
But please, please ask,
ask and try to experiment.
Now it's much more easy.
When I started these things,
the only way was installing a ton of
things and learn,
study the full book and then you start.
Now you can ask and dig and try to learn
by your own.
Questions.
Can you show me now an example of
quotations in F sharp? By the way,
by the way, if you're wondering how I.
Became involved in F#.
It was because my of my PhD thesis around.
Code generation in java and.
net basically and and and and and and and
so I was asked to review this thing by
the author of the language.
So.
Well,
quotation server part was similar to Lisp
because today I I just asked about Lisp
because it was easy to say OK.
Uh.
The output of the quotation,
it's more complicated to define in the
sense that I hope that by now you you
appreciate the difference between having
an interpreter or not,
because if you have the interpreter,
basically you are able to generate code.
And execute the code at runtime.
Lisp was made that way.
Then they were also Lisp compilers.
But basically whenever you got a
quotation in Lisp or a quasi quotation in
Lisp, the compiler Lisp.
Program contained also a Lisp interpreter
to interpret the part of this that was
not possible to compile.
The same apply to JavaScript.
JavaScript is P code these days,
but still you can write JavaScript code
that can be compiled and so at runtime.
We also have the full interpreter and
then the full interpreter tries to
optimize which version should be executed.
OK, so.
In F# you can quote the syntax here is
angle brackets and F,
but basically you can quote part of the
program.
By using quotation you can delay the
execution of the code.
So there are several ways of looking at
this thing.
One way is to say when this 1 + 2 should
be evaluated.
Now now please that should be quoted and
then if I have a run operation then I
will say run code.
And the code will be executed.
Why?
Because most of our programming languages
have a a eager, eager evaluation strategy.
So when you write.
Yeah.
A function in invocation in Java.
Net Ross pick up almost whatever you want
if you write add 1 + 2.
Uh.
Three, not two.
When this 1 + 2 will be evaluated.
Before.
The execution of other or later before.
That is not the only option.
You can say you know what?
As long as I don't need the first
argument,
I can suspend the execution and I will
evaluate only if needed. OK,
that is another option that is lazy
execution.
Asker supports lazy execution.
Why are we using basically almost only
eager execution strategy?
Because it's more efficient to implement.
And in fact, after many attempts,
Askel always struggled to have an
efficient implementation, right?
We still wondering why people is using
Python and not ask it because Python is
less efficient than ask it,
but it's also less expressive. Sorry.
So quotations are a way in programming
languages to get back a lazy about do
insertion strategy in which the language
is eager, so you don't you're not paid.
For laziness, if it's not needed,
and if it's needed,
you quote the code and say OK,
I will use the operator to run the code
when I need it, right?
Of course the implementation of the run
operator requires you to have.
Basically the compiler is something
similar at runtime,
so it's not for free the run operation.
OK,
but nevertheless you can obtain the thing.
So you see when you quote the expression.
And then you print the expression you
have the.
A sort of a variant of a an S expression.
So you have basically the compiler
generates for you.
And that structure which represents the
code. So here is call of addition.
With these arguments, Sir.
Hmm.
And of course you also have variables
quoted.
And in this case.
The un quote is implicit.
That is the decision of the.
So I'm using ** is 10 and this will be
unquoted automatically by the language
and so as you can see there is not at
least.
No, sorry, I said a wrong thing.
I mean it is unquoted, yes.
I was wondering this lead.
I think that this is an hallucination.
Because let X10 is outside of the court,
so.
You want to see a guy hallucinating that
it is. This is wrong, OK?
Next the quotation.
Like Lisp, et cetera.
So if you want to un quote,
then you're not using a single ad,
but you use two ads and then you can.
Have placeholder that will be evaluated
now and not deferred. OK,
so you have part of your expression that
is will be evaluated when you use run and
part now because you're saying percent
percentage in there and in this case you
are splicing in.
The the inner why these two things are
useful? Because for instance,
if you want to compose a program,
often you will say if the data has this
property then I need this fragment of
code,
otherwise I need another equivalent
fragment of code. OK, so.
Usually you do the splicing,
so you say OK,
the code is take the code inner,
remove the quotation,
put here the code and then the rest is
quoted and so I can combine fragments of
code in an algebra of code manipulation.
That is also type safe because in this
case the code the the language is capable
of type inferencing the code and say this
code is of type int and this code
requires a code of type int and return a.
Code of typing so you can even type check
the thing.
OK.
So.
There are evaluation for the quotation,
but these are not complete in F sharp.
So in general, when you go to reflection,
when you go to intersection,
you always have to.
Keep in mind that the first question is
how much can I reflect at runtime and how
much I can act at runtime?
Because unless it's an interpreter and in
case of the interpreter,
typically you can do.
Almost everything in all the other
programming languages,
there is a compromise.
So in Java you can reflect the type
system, not the body of the method. In.
net you can reflect the type system.
You can even reflect the body methods,
but those will be expressed in.
Intermediate language,
not in the language you wrote the code.
OK,
so it's a compromise for efficiency
purpose and the same applies to the
quotations and the code.
So unless you don't want to have the full
language support at runtime,
you may have a system this helper that.
Comes with F# allows you to evaluate the
quotation,
but it will not support the full language.
So if you use some unsupported language
feature that may be supported by the
quotation,
you will get an error when you want to
evaluate that.
OK. And that is part of life.
OK, um.
Now that we, uh, look into that, can um.
And we finished and we we will start
tomorrow from here,
but can you show me an example?
Of.
Uh,
an expression evaluation of F quotation.
So when you have quotation,
typically you have data structure which
represents the code no,
which is basically the syntax tree that
the parser generates generate in terms of
data of your language.
Um, so you can write your own interpreter.
Enough.
I know.
No, no, no, no, no.
I need the uh.
A recursive evaluation example with
pattern matching.
Don't use.
BF sharp evaluation.
Why is this useless as an example?
OK.
So.
Basically you suddenly start appreciating
all the things we said about grammars,
because basically you are browsing the
abstract syntax tree that is generated by
the language.
Into a data structure and in rogramming
languages.
With the button matching like F sharp,
like list like like Askel,
ML and many others,
basically you can say OK.
I I I have the ability to structure a
match values and so I can say match the
expression with if the expression is a
value with some value and I don't care
the rest.
The result is value OK if it's call.
And the know the the with some operation
and the name is addition and I have two
values A and B.
Then I convert at runtime A and B and.
And I call.
Beware I call eval,
so I recurse because this can be an
expression itself so.
Like in the grammar.
Call it can can be plaza expression
expression and you recourse so I can
recursively go.
Eventually I know I will get an integer
and then I.
Box the result.
Which is the sum of the two values.
If it's multiply, do the multiplication.
If it's if then else,
then eval the condition into bool and
then eval the then or the branch.
And so on so.
Of course,
if you want to interpret at runtime,
either you have the full compiler,
otherwise you can retain a much lighter
version,
which is something that is able at
compile time to generate the tree. OK,
so the compiler at compile time generates
the.
Expression structure inside the and don't
need anymore the F compiler because you
already got the result and then I
interpret the thing again. Why we do this?
Because this allows.
Even for compiled languages to have some
code manipulation without having to bring
the full compiler stack at runtime,
which of course will be the alternative.
In that case you output the F sharp,
you call the compiler, that's it,
you can execute OK, but that is too much,
it's too expensive.
It's too error prone.
In this way you can even prove properties.
You can prove that the system is not
broken,
you can forbid to use language features
that in other cases are applicable,
and so on.
OK.
Right. I think we can.
Stop here and tomorrow we will start
again and we will finish to reason about
meta programming and look into many other
application of these techniques.
Thank you.